[indistinct radio chatter]
[sirens wailing in distance]
Excuse me.
Can I get a comment, please?
Yes, ma'am,
keep it right back here.
[helicopter flying overhead]
- Captain.
- Agent Lisbon.
Don't think
we'll be needing you guys.
'We like the neighbor kid
who found the body.'
- Did he confess?
- Ah, he's a real squirrel.
- Did you kill her?
Did you kill her?
[male #1]
'Mercy's father would like
to give a brief statement.'
I just want to take a moment
and thank everyone
in law enforcement
and all the volunteers
who helped us in the search
for our beloved daughter.
'The way that this
entire community'
has come together
to support me and Juniper
in this terrible time
has been a great comfort to us.
'And now I would just
like to ask you that..'
'..you give us some time,
space and privacy'
'to grieve for our daughter.'
'Thank you.'
[indistinct radio chatter]
[rustling]
[teakettle whistling]
[whistling stops]
Hello, Mrs. Tolliver.
Who are you?
My name is Patrick Jane.
I'm here to help you.
Would you like a cup of tea?
Yes, I would, thank you.
You must be tired.
Why don't you sit down?
It's nice and quiet
in here, isn't it?
Quiet, soothing, calm.
Calm.
[sighs]
I've been watching you
and your husband
and I want you to know
that I understand
what you're feeling
right now.
You have no idea.
Believe me.
I do.
I know.
I know,
and I wanna help you.
You can't help me.
You..
What do you know?
[chuckles]
All sorts of things.
You really only pretend
to like skiing, right?
Yes, but--
You're pleased
that your best friend
recently gained some weight.
About 10 pounds.
You wish you'd been
more adventurous
when you were younger.
You love India,
but you've never been there.
You have trouble sleeping.
Your favorite color..
...is blue.
I don't understand.
You're..
You're psychic?
[chuckles]
No.
Just paying attention.
I used to make a good living
pretending to be a psychic.
I tell you this because
I want you to understand
there's no point
hiding things from me.
Hiding...what?
You know what I see
when I look at your husband?
I see a warm, loving,
generous man.
A little vain, maybe.
Selfish, controlling..
...but a decent man.
Yes.
So why do you suspect him
of murdering your daughter?
[teacup rattling]
I don't.
- The McCluskey boy did it.
- Yes.
That's what the police say.
But you think
they're wrong. Why?
I don't know.
I-I-I don't know.
I..
Tell me.
Last year,
they-they have been
so strange with each other.
And neither one would admit
that anything was wrong
and I think that..
I think that she tried
to tell me once
and I didn't..
I...
God.
Oh, God.
Did you ask him
if he killed her?
[sniffles]
What would he say?
Most wives can tell
when their husbands are lying.
Yes. Yes. I..
I don't want tea. I..
The McCluskey boy did it. I..
Maybe.
[whispers]
Oh.
You think he did it, too?
I trust a mother's instinct.
[door opens]
June?
[sighs]
'There you are.'
Hi. Who are you?
I'm the police.
Did you kill your daughter?
[scoffs]
How dare you?
I asked you
a simple question, sir.
Did you kill your daughter?
- No.
- Oh!
I did not kill my daughter!
Now you get the hell
out of my house!
June?
June, what's the matter
with you?
I'm gonna have your badge.
An innocent man
would have punched me by now.
I am gonna make life
miserable for you.
You come in here,
you accost my wife
you cause trouble on..
[cocks pistol]
June.
June, honey, please.
[gunshots fired]
[officers shouting
indistinctly]
[male #2]
'Move! Move! Hey!'
Honestly, it-it's not
as bad as it looks.
[indistinct radio chatter]
Mrs. Tolliver?
Mrs. Tolliver!
Please wait.
[male #2]
Front room's clear!
Then the son of a bitch
eagles 17.
Are you kiddin' me?
On that course?
A damn eagle?
That course never
suited you, Price.
We'll do better in Orlando.
We have a nice spot on the draw.
Well, I'll tell you what.
Davis Love III
can kiss my butt.
[male #3]
Alison?
Alison!
[indistinct chatter]
[woman over PA]
'Flight 233 from Sacramento'
'you may claim your baggage
from carousel 2.'
'Flight 233 from Sacramento...'
Uh, sorry.
You checked luggage?
What are you, on vacation?
No, ma'am.
Won't do it again.
When your trousseau arrives,
pick up the second rental
and go direct
to the sheriff's department
hustle us up a couple of rooms,
furniture and phone lines.
Yes. Ma'am.
Come on. Let's go.
[Lisbon sighs]
Morning, everybody.
How was your flight?
Go away.
You're on suspension.
Thank you.
Mandated leave.
Ends next week.
So come back next week.
Hot enough for you?
Which one of you jackasses
told him?
- It was you, wasn't it, Cho?
- Yes, it was.
Of course he called me.
It's Red John.
You can't keep me out of this.
Why would you want to?
You got a man killed.
There's consequences.
Oh, a man
that murdered his daughter
'cause she wouldn't have sex
with him anymore?
You didn't know that.
You didnotknow that.
If she hadn't had left
a diary--
But she did, though.
Be reasonable. This is my case.
- Your case?
- Red John's mine.
Red john
doesn't belong to anyone.
[sighs]
He belongs to me.
It's not my call.
Rules are rules.
Come back next week.
Don't let this man past.
[cell phone rings]
[ring]
[beep]
Boss?
We have Gregory Tannen
Caucasian, male,
43, single.
'We haven't opened him up yet,
but burn marks..'
Sorry I went over your head.
I'll redeem myself, I promise.
You want redemption?
Be silent.
- Okay. I can learn to do that.
- Shh!
Sorry.
The burn marks here
indicate that the victim
'was subdued with a stun gun'
'standard civilian model
by the look of it.'
Death appears to be caused
by several blows
to the back of the skull
'consistent with a bloodied
golf club found at the scene.'
'Female is Alison Randolph
27, married, no children.'
'They were found
at her listed residence.'
'TOD looks to be
early Saturday evening.'
'On Alison, we have
the same stun gun marks'
'followed by binding with
tight black plastic ligatures'
frenzied cutting and stabbing
assault of the torso
and subsequent abuse
of the viscera.
- Textbook Red John.
- Who found the bodies?
This one's husband, coming home
from the airport Sunday morning
'with his brother.
He's a pro golfer.'
- Oh, yeah?
- Price Randolph.
What's her deal with him?
Do we know?
Uh, he's on file
as one of her physicians.
- Making a house call?
- Lovers?
No, this one's gay.
Dr. Wagner might know
what their relationship was.
He's here
to make the formal I.D.?
Okay.
Dr. Wagner.
Hi.
I'm Agent Teresa Lisbon
California bureau
of investigation.
What's your connection
to the victims?
I work with Gregory.
Dr. Tannen and-and
the Randolph family
are longtime clients
of our practice.
Are house calls the norm
at your practice?
No. Gregory and Alison
were close friends.
- Lovers?
- No. He was gay.
No, they were just...
friends.
What in God's name
happened to them?
Looks like Red John.
Who's Red John?
We don't know who did this.
We'll be in touch probably.
Thank you.
- 'Set up right here?'
- 'Yeah, that's good.'
Red John enters here.
Excuse me. Sorry.
He comes around here.
'He waits for her..'
'...expecting her
to come in alone.'
Only thing, her friend Tannen
Chose the wrong night
to come over for a Richard Gere
and ice cream orgy.
So Red John zaps 'em both
with his trusty stun gun
and...
...excuse me.
Grabs a 5-iron
from the bag here and..
Bam!
Crushes Tannen's skull.
'Then he takes his sweet time'
'dealing with Alison
how he likes.'
She's a nice big girl,
so unless he's pretty strong
'I'm guessing that he grabbed
her by the arms and...'
He says he's sorry
for all the pain
he's caused you
and your mother.
Deeply sorry.
[woman sniffles]
He asks you to forgive him.
Can you do that, Jenny?
[crying]
Mm-hmm.
- He needs to hear it.
- I forgive you, daddy.
- Oh, yes.
- Daddy, I forgive you.
[cries]
He's smiling now.
[laughs]
They're tears of joy.
[cries]
He says, "God bless you
and keep you."
[continues crying]
He's gone.
Amazing. Amazing. Amazing.
She's...amazed.
[laughter]
- Patrick..
- One second.
- Give him some time.
- Ab-absolu..
Come on back to us.
- I'm back. Thank you.
- He's back.
So, Patrick, I understand
that you're also
sort of a paranormal
detective. Is that right?
I try to help the police
when I can.
And-and you're
helping them hunt
this scary serial killer.
What's his name?
- Red--
- Red john?
- There she blows..
- Classic Red John smiley face.
Drawn in the victims' blood
clockwise with three fingers
of his right hand
wearing a rubber
kitchen glove.
I'm stoked to finally
see one in the flesh.
This isn't Red John.
Right.
Red john thinks of himself
as a showman, an artist.
'He has a strong sense
of theater.'
In all the previous killings,
he made sure
that the first thing that anyone
sees is the face on the wall.
'You see the face first,
and you know..'
'...you know what's happened,
and you feel dread.'
Then and only then do you see
the body of the victim.
'Always in that order.'
Here it's the opposite.
The first thing you see
is the body
and you have to look around
to see the face on the wall.
Doesn't play nearly
as well, does it?
Depends on your taste,
I suppose.
No, come on. The killer
could have painted
on the correct wall here,
but he didn't
because he didn't know better
because he isn't Red John.
Wow. It's interesting.
[sighs deeply]
You know what
your problem is, my friend?
You enjoy your work a little
too much. You're a ghoul.
If you don't get horny
reading "Fangoria"
I'm Britney Spears.
I-I resent that.
This is you trying
to redeem yourself, is it?
I'm sorry.
He irks me.
He's irksome.
You don't need me here.
So, yeah, this one
doesn't fit the pattern.
So Jane was right.
We have a copycat.
Or we have Red John
trying new things
'or we have Red John
making a mistake.'
We don't know. We'll work
the evidence until we do know.
- Go talk to the husband.
- Will do, boss.
What are you waitin' for?
[dialing]
Hey. So you might be right
about this case.
Might be.
Thanks for the insight.
No. Did I say that?
I'm acknowledging the fact that
you might be right, that's all.
I mean, if you wanted
to come back
I couldn't stop you.
Yeah, fine.
I'm asking you to come back.
Because.
Because you're useful
to the team.
No. No, I won't say "please."
Go screw yourself.
[beep]
Jackass.
[Jane]
'Good morning.'
Can I help you?
You must be Van Pelt.
Pleasure. Patrick Jane.
Oh, hi. Good to meet you.
Agent Cho said
you had left town.
No. Nowhere to go.
Okay. Um..
Do you want that desk
over there or this one?
I mean,
that one gets more light.
That one.
More light by all means.
[chuckles]
Very pleasant addition
to the serious crimes family.
Oh. Hi.
When did you get here?
Oh!Stop. I give up. Ooh!
'Stop. Please, stop.
Turn off the camera.'
'Come on, come on, come on.'
'Okay, we're done, we're done.'
'You are just awful!'
Okay.
Go, go, go.
'Stop, please. Stop!'
[click]
I lost a beautiful,
precious angel.
Yes, sir.
Good-looking woman.
[clears throat]
I'm jumping right in
if you don't mind, Price.
'You missed the tournament
cut on Friday, yes?'
'But you didn't come home
until Sunday.'
What did you do with the rest
of your time in Fresno?
I get this. You-you guys can't
catch the real killer
so you wanna
lay this one on me?
No, sir. If we have that
confirmation of where you were
it lets us exclude you
from the investigation.
[chuckles]
I was with a massage therapist.
Name?
Uh...it had "lady"
in there somewhere.
It'll be
on his credit card bill.
'There you go.'
Pleasure meeting you boys.
[Wagner]
'We're a full-service
private practice.'
'We deliver primary care'
'uh, cosmetic surgery'
psychotherapy, sports medicine..
You name it.
What's the African connection?
It's what
this place is all about.
Half our profits
go to build and staff
basic health clinics
in poor African communities.
Ah, here we are.
[sighs]
'It's a thin file.'
'Alison was
a healthy young woman.'
Psychiatric history?
She didn't have one.
[Lisbon]
'STDS? Abortions?'
'Unexplained injuries?'
[Wagner]
'No. Except for some
routine checkups with me'
'it's all Dr. Tannen.
All aesthetic work.'
Did Tannen keep a diary?
Our last case was solved
because the victim kept a diary.
Diary? I don't think so.
Getting back
to Alison Randolph...
'how was her marriage,
do you think?'
Happy? Unhappy?
About six months ago
Dr. Tannen asked my advice.
'Alison had asked him
to get her'
a year's supply
of birth control pills
off the books, which is
strictly against AMA Code.
'I said sure, do it.'
'I mean, better us
than some Tijuana drugstore.
Why the secrecy?
Price Randolph had
a vasectomy, April of '02.
[chuckles]
If there's anything else
I can do...
I appreciate that.
Actually, there is. Uh..
I'm out of sleeping pills.
Can you fix me up?
Anything strong will do.
Sure. Uh, come in
for a consultation.
We'll squeeze you in
this afternoon.
Oh, no. I-I was hoping
to get something now.
Trying to avoid the chitchat.
I'm sorry.
I wouldn't feel
comfortable prescribing
without some sort
of "chitchat."
I understand.
Uh, no problem.
I'll call you..
...maybe.
[Cho]
'I like the husband for it.'
'He hires some hooker he knows
to create an alibi'
flies home, fillets the spouse,
flies back again.
The classic elaborate and clever
but ultimately stupid plan.
Have you looked at
his PGA tournament record?
It's not bad.
6 mil career earnings.
Mm-hmm, for coming in
second and third.
'You put him on the 18th tee
with a big one on the line'
like night follows day,
he'll shank it. He's a Choker.
He doesn't have the nerve
to kill his wife. Didn't do it.
Mm.
Are you suggesting
we drop a prime suspect
'because he's never
won a major?'
'Oh, no, no, no. I'm just
making idle conversation.'
How'd you do that?
Telekinesis.
He blew on it.
That is another way
to do it.
Mr. Jane..
...I have a question regarding
your previous career path.
Fire away.
When you met with other
psychics, real psychics
could they tell
you were just pretending?
There's no such thing
as real psychics.
I beg to differ.
My cousin Yolanda is a psychic.
Your cousin is deluded
or dishonest, or both.
Hey. Steady.
No, no, he's entitled
to his opinion.
He's wrong, though.
She has power.
Thank you.
She can communicate
with the other side.
I've seen her do it myself.
She let you speak
with someone that's gone.
Yes.
Someone that you love
and still miss very much.
Yes.
You wanted her power
to be real, so it was.
No.
You're so sure you're right.
Science don't know everything.
500 years ago, radio would've
seemed like magic.
Exactly.
500 years in the future,
it could be totally normal to
communicate with the other side.
- The "other side."
- Mm-hmm.
Your father's
a football coach, yeah?
How'd you know that?
It's obvious
from your whole demeanor.
My point is, didn't dad always
say life is like football?
When that final whistle blows,
the game is over.
Done. There is no more.
There is no "other side."
this is it..
Lobster and bread rolls
and nautical kitsch.
And then...nothingness.
You poor, sad man.
The kingdom of God
is a real place.
Okay, later tonight,
when Rigsby asks you to
come back to his hotel room..
[choking and coughing]
- ...say yes.
- Excuse me?
I know. You were planning on
refusing him very curtly.
First week on the job,
you wanna set a tone.
No monkey business.
But why not?
Rigsby is an excellent lover,
I'm sure.
[sighs]
Tough but fair. Right?
Right.
The kingdom of God
is a real place, Mr. Jane
and you have
an immortal soul.
Oh, I do so hope
you're wrong.
[elevator bell chimes]
- Goodnight.
Later, dude.
[elevator bell dings]
This is... me.
[elevator bell chimes]
Welcome to the unit,
Agent Van Pelt.
Thank you, agent Rigsby.
[male narrator on TV]
She explodes into action,
reaching up
to 60 miles per hour.
She easily outruns
her terrifying prey.
[panting]
Oh!
[alarm blaring]
"Greetings, old friend.
It's been a while.
"I hope you are keeping well.
I am thriving and happy.
"I have 12 wives now and will
soon begin courting number 13.
"Why can't you catch me?
"You must feel so powerless
and stupid and sad.
"Oh, well.
All the best. Red John."
That sounds like
the real deal to me.
Sounds like Red John.
It's not.
Red John wouldn't risk capture
just to taunt me.
So the real killer's
trying to throw us off-track?
Cho, find out where Price
Randolph was a half an hour ago.
'Rigsby, I want you to check
the hotel security cameras.'
'Get those over to forensics.'
You okay?
Absolutely.
Get some sleep.
[door closes]
[telephone rings]
[ring]
Hello?
- Good morning.
- You didn't sleep, did you?
[slurping]
Hi. I-I'd like
to make an appointment
with Dr. Wagner, please.
It's urgent.
'Jane. Patrick Jane.'
Yeah, I'll hold.
Forensics maybe got a break.
The blood on the cloth
in the envelope
is Alison Randolph's.
But they found a hair in there..
Doesn't belong to her or Tannen.
Guess who
it doesbelong to.
It's yours, Tag.
Amazing, huh?
Science.
This is insane.
I didn't...
'I didn't kill Alison.'
[Cho]
'How do you explain
your hair in the envelope?'
Either it was a mistake
'or-or I'm being framed.'
'Who would want to frame you?'
'We don't want to, if that's
what you're thinking.'
[whispers]
He and Alison were lovers.
Who would want to
frame you, Tag?
My brother.
[Cho]
'Why would he want
to do that?'
Alison and I were lovers.
I think youarepsychic.
You're just afraid to admit it.
Mm-hmm.
So..
[clears throat]
Why is it
you can't sleep?
Because I can't
get the good pills
without talking to a doctor.
Hmm.
And you don't like
talking to doctors.
Meh, you know,
they always wanna be
the smartest person in the room,
don't they?
When in fact that's me,
obviously.
You protect your core self
very fiercely.
What do you think
is the reason for that?
[chuckles]
You know, this is exactly
how I imagined it would be.
You gonna ask me
about my mother?
Do you want me
to ask you about your mother?
I just wanna sleep.
So what is it
that keeps you awake?
[male #4]
'What's his name?
Red john?'
That's right. Red John.
Uh, he's-he's killed at least
eight women that we know of.
Uh, the police asked me to try
and get a psychic fix on him
to see if I could get
a sense of who this man is.
Uh, how do you do that exactly,
get a psychic fix on someone?
Well, Davis
true demonic evil
burns like fire.
It-it burns with
a terrible cold, dark flame.
I force myself
to look into that flame
and I see an image
of the evildoer..
In this case, Red John.
He's an ugly,
tormented little man.
A lonely soul.
Sad, very sad.
"Dear Mr. Jane, I do not like
to be slandered in the media
"especially by
a dirty money-grubbing fraud.
"if you are a real psychic
"instead of
a dishonest little worm
"you wouldn't need to open
the door to see
what I've done to
your lovely wife and child."
[door creaks]
[Wagner]
'Mr. Jane?'
'What is it
that keeps you awake?'
[sighs deeply]
Um.. \
You know, when I was a boy,
we had a farm.
It's a lot of work.
I was kind of a lazy kid.
Yes?
I'd always be trying
to get my little brother Jimmy
to do my Chores for me.
One day, I promised him a dollar
if he'd cut the firewood.
Hmm.
'Well..'
'he opened up an artery
in his leg on the saw'
'and he bled to death..'
...died..
...doing my Chores for me.
You know..
that's almost
exactly the same thing
that happened to Johnny Cash.
Is it really?
'Wow.'
That's spooky.
Mr. Randolph, good--
Cut the crap.
My brother's done nothing.
And you scumbags haven't got
the stones to come after me
so you come after my family.
That is flat-out persecution.
Price, what did we agree?
Mr. Randolph, rest assured,
there's no intent
to persecute you.
We scumbags are holding
your brother
because we have
physical evidence
linking him to the crime
and potential motive
in that he states that
whenever you weren't around
he was banging your wife
like a big bass drum.
[laughs]
Tag and Alison?
That's what he states,
and he further states
that it was you
that killed Alison
'and you're now trying
to frame him in revenge.'
What'd you say? Wh..
Bastard!
[Van Pelt]
'Hey.'
Aah! Son of a bitch!
[Tag]
'You treated her like
trash! What did you expect?'
I didn't expect my little
brother to be banging my wife!
You little punk bastard!
Everything you've told me
is total fiction, isn't it?
Yes.
Why?
I can tell
you're in real pain.
Why not tell the truth?
The truth is mine.
- I hear ya.
- Thank you.
Oh. Yes.
Remember, uh, we were talking
about Tannen the other day
and I asked you if he kept
a diary, and you said he did?
Well, there's no diary
among his effects.
- No.
- I'm sorry, no?
No. You have it wrong.
I-I didn't think
he kept a diary.
Strange. Then it must have been
someone else who told me.
Either that
or I'm going mad.
But I definitely,
100% remember hearing
that Tannen kept a diary.
Well, that is strange
but why does it matter
if he kept a diary?
You're right.
It doesn't matter.
Only I was thinking
why do magicians have
beautiful girl assistants?
Why?
Because they're reliable
distracters of attention.
People will look at a beautiful
girl for a long time
before they look
where they should be looking
if they wanna see
how the trick really works.
[both chuckle]
Anyhow, I'll send over a couple
of forensics guys tomorrow
to search his office
and locate that diary.
Mm, didn't they already
search his office?
Oh, they never do it
thoroughly the first time.
Once more for luck, eh?
It's gotta be there somewhere.
Thanks for everything, doc.
- Goodnight.
Lost something?
- How did you get in?
- Door was open.
I think I left my phone
in your office.
- The door wasn't open.
- Must have been. Here I am.
What are you doing?
[sighs]
I confess, the temptation
to play detective
was a little too strong.
I..
I was looking
for that diary.
I got a little
carried away.
No kidding.
No diary?
No diary.
Maybe I should have a gander.
I'm good at finding things.
Be my guest.
Hmm.
[grunts]
[sighs]
Eureka.
Dr. Wagner,
thanks for your help.
Mr. Jane.
Uh, your phone.
Right.
Thanks.
Uh, yeah. Got it.
Silly of me.
Well, good-bye again.
Wait.
Give me the diary.
- It's very amusing.
- I try.
[inhales sharply]
I knew. I knew it might
be a trick, but I..
I had to be sure.
Yes. That's how
the trick works.
What led you to me?
Not that I'm saying I did it.
I'm just asking.
When we first met, you said you
didn't know who Red John was
but you have books
on criminal psychiatry
there..
that have chapters on him.
You're the Randolph
family doctor
so you could easily
get a strand of Tag's hair
and, being a doctor,
you could hack up another human
without difficulty.
It's obvious it was you.
[scoffs]
That's it?
You have nothing.
That's just guesswork.
Oh, I know.
I just wanted to be sure
I had the right answer.
I was surprised.
I gotta be honest.
You don't seem to be
a wicked man.
But you are.
[chuckles]
You're angry
about the letter.
Yeah, it was
a bit mean-spirited.
For the record,
I'm sorry about your family
I can only imagine
your pain.
I'm not...a wicked man.
My conscience is clear.
Really?
Right now in Africa,
there's 3,000 beautiful children
alive today who should be dead,
but they aren't because of me.
Tannen was gonna ruin me
and destroy all that work..
...over nothing.
Money.
"Theft," he called it.
"Embezzlement."
Self-righteous idiot.
It's simple math.
If I go to jail,
thousands of kids will die.
So I made
a rational, moral decision
to kill Tannen..
...for the greater good.
And Alison?
What did she do wrong?
Mm.
[electricity crackles]
As you said, she was
the magician's assistant
just a distraction.
Oh.
If only Tannen died,
the police would've been
all over this place,
wouldn't they?
Truly, is killing two
any worse than killing one,
when so many lives are at stake?
I don't think so.
You poor, sad man.
You're under arrest.
Let's go.
I'm pointing a gun at you.
You really think
I would set you up so nicely
and let you pull
a loaded gun on me?
I took the bullets
out earlier.
[metal clinks]
- You're late!
- What?
- Draw your weapon!
- Huh?
Drop the gun!
'Hands on your head.'
Get down on your knees.
Down.
[gun slides across floor]
[laughs]
[indistinct radio chatter]
Closed case doughnuts
are here.
I just went to get
sleeping pills, I swear to god.
I-I didn't evenwannago.
You know I didn't want to go.
Right.
Yeah, you didn't
set Wagner up..
...didn't figure
it was him days ago.
You didn't let us
tear apart the victim's family
simply to satisfy
your childish need for drama.
Meh, that family
was screwed anyway.
Don't blame yourselves, guys.
[siren wailing in distance]
Don't even start.
I'm still angry.
- I'm sorry.
- No, you're not.
A frog?
Well, this makes everything
better, doesn't it?
[gasps]
[keys drop on table]
[grunts]
[sighs]